heartmath.org 2006-12-20

# Privacy Policy Statement of Institute of Heartmath

[  
](http://www.heartmath.org/universe/index.html)Institute of HeartMath Privacy Policy Statement 

This statement discloses the privacy practices for Institute of HeartMath web sites.

**We agree to notify you of:**

1\. What personally identifiable information of yours or third party personally identifiable information is collected from you through the web site

2\. The organization collecting the information

3\. How the information is used

4\. With whom the information may be shared

5\. What choices are available to you regarding collection, use and distribution of the information

6\. The kind of security procedures that are in place to protect the loss, misuse or alteration of information under the Institute of HeartMath's control

7\. How you can correct any inaccuracies in the information. 

If you feel that this company is not abiding by its posted privacy policy, you should first contact Brian Kabaker, Director of Sales and Marketing, by phone at 866-221-6339 / 831-338-8500 or e-mail at [bkabaker@heartmath.org](mailto:bkabaker@heartmath.org).

**Information Collection and Use**  
Institute of HeartMath is the sole owner of the information collected on this site. We will not sell, share, or rent this information to others in ways different from what is disclosed in this statement. Institute of HeartMath collects information from our users at several different points on our web site.

**Registration**  
In order to access certain features of this web site, a user may be required to complete a registration form. During registration, a user is required to give his/her contact information (such as name and e-mail address). This information is used to contact the user about the services on our site in which they have expressed interest.

**Orders and Donations**  
We request information from the user on our order form and donation form. Here a user must provide contact information (like name and address) and financial information (like credit card number, expiration date). This information is used for billing purposes, to fill customers' orders or send a donation receipt. If we have trouble processing an order or a donation, this contact information is used to get in touch with the user.

**Cookies**  
A cookie is a piece of data stored on the user's hard drive containing information about the user. Usage of a cookie is in no way linked to any personally identifiable information while on our site. Once the user closes their browser, the cookie simply terminates. Our web shopping cart utilizes cookies to facilitate the ordering process; our login service uses session cookies to remember subscriber login information.

**Log Files**  
We use Internet Protocol (IP) addresses to analyze trends, administer the site, track users' movements, and gather broad demographic information for aggregate use. IP addresses are not linked to personally identifiable information.

**  
Sharing**  
We will share aggregated demographic information with our partners and advertisers. This is not linked to any personal information that can identify any individual person.

We use an outside shipping company to ship orders, and a credit card processing company to bill users for goods and services. These companies do not retain, share, store or use personally identifiable information for any secondary purposes.

We partner with another party to provide specific services. When the user signs up for these services, we will share names, or other contact information that is necessary for the third party to provide these services.

These parties are not allowed to use personally identifiable information except for the purpose of providing these services.

**  
Links**  
This web site contains links to other sites. Please be aware that we, the Institute of HeartMath are not responsible for the privacy practices of such other sites. We encourage our users to be aware when they leave our site and to read the privacy statements of each and every web site that collects personally identifiable information. This privacy statement applies solely to information collected by this web site.

**  
Mailing Lists**  
If a user wishes to subscribe to any of our mailing lists, we ask for contact information such as name and e-mail address.

**Surveys & Contests**  
From time-to-time our site requests information from users via surveys or contests. Participation in these surveys or contests is completely voluntary and the user therefore has a choice whether or not to disclose this information. Information requested may include contact information (such as name and shipping address), and demographic information (such as zip code, age level). Contact information will be used to notify the winners and award prizes. Survey information will be used for purposes of monitoring or improving the use and satisfaction of this site.

**Tell-A-Friend**  
If a user elects to use our referral service for informing a friend about our site, we ask them for the friend's name and e-mail address. Institute of HeartMath will automatically send the friend a one-time e-mail inviting him or her to visit the site. Institute of HeartMath stores this information for the sole purpose of sending this one-time e-mail. The friend may contact Institute of HeartMath at [ihminquiry@heartmath.org](mailto:ihminquiry@heartmath.org) to request the removal of this information from their database.

**Security**  
This web site takes every precaution to protect our users' information. When users submit sensitive information via the web site, your information is protected both on-line and off-line.

When our registration/order form asks users to enter sensitive information, such as a credit card number, that information is encrypted and is protected with the best encryption software in the industry - SSL. While on a secure page, such as our order form, the lock icon on the bottom of web browsers, such as Netscape Navigator and Microsoft Internet Explorer, becomes locked, as opposed to un-locked, or open, when you are just "surfing."

While we use SSL encryption to protect sensitive information on-line, we also do everything in our power to protect user-information off-line. All of our users' information, not just the sensitive information mentioned above, is restricted in our offices. Only employees who need the information to perform a specific job (for example, our billing clerk or a customer service representative) are granted access to personally identifiable information. 

Furthermore, ALL employees are kept up-to-date on our security and privacy practices. Every quarter, as well as any time new policies are added, our employees are notified and/or reminded about the importance we place on privacy, and what they can do to ensure our customers' information is protected.

If you have any questions about the security at our web site, you can send an e-mail to [security@heartmath.org](mailto:security@heartmath.org).

**Special Offers**  
Customers and clients will occasionally receive information on products, services, special deals, and a newsletter. Out of respect for the privacy of our users we present the option to not receive these types of communications. Please see our choice and opt-out below.

**Correction/Updating Personal Information**  
If a user's personally identifiable information changes (such as your zip code), or if a user no longer desires our service, we will endeavor to provide a way to correct, update or remove that user's personal data provided to us. This can usually be done at the member information page or by e-mailing our Customer Support.

**Choice/Opt-out**  
Our users are given the opportunity to "opt-out" of having their information used for purposes not directly related to our site at the point where we ask for the information. For example, our order form has an "opt-out" mechanism so users who buy a product from us, but don't want any marketing material, can prevent their e-mail address from being added to our lists.

Users who no longer wish to receive our newsletter or promotional materials from our partners may opt-out of receiving these communications by replying to "unsubscribe" in the subject line in the e-mail or e-mail us at [optout@heartmath.org](mailto:optout@heartmath.org).

Users of our site are always notified when their information is being collected by any outside parties. We do this so our users can make an informed choice as to whether they should proceed with services that require an outside party, or not.

**Notification of Changes**  
We will use information in accordance with the privacy policy under which the information was collected. If we decide to change our privacy policy, we will post those changes on our Homepage so our users are always aware of what information we collect, how we use it, and under what circumstances, if any, we disclose it. If at any point we decide to use personally identifiable information in a manner different from that stated at the time it was collected, we will notify users by way of an e-mail. Users will have a reasonable time frame to respond with their choice as to whether or not we use their information in this different manner.

   Printer Friendly Version Available
